Hey, Brandon here with the final lecture
in my writing lecture series, writing
science fiction, fantasy. This is the
final Q&A. We're going to cover anything
anyone wants to know from me. So, last
lecture, you made it all the way. Hey,
welcome to your last
[Applause]
class. This is the end of writing
science fiction fantasy. um if you have
one of those waiverss, make sure to drop
it off before you leave. Um put it up
here and if you haven't signed one, we'd
appreciate it. All right, so this is the
final big Q&A. This is um I've got some
of your questions on here that'll seat
us and get us started. And then you get
to ask me whatever you want for our last
class period here. Except you, you don't
get to ask
anything. He he's one of my employees. I
can do that.
Um, so we're going to begin with if you
were breaking in now as a new author,
how would you go about doing
it? This is an excellent question and um
it's a hard one to answer. For the
longest time, I recommended a hybrid
approach uh that I recommended. This was
back when indie publishing was working
just a little bit better than it is now.
Um, I would recommend that authors write
a book and if they were interested in
both traditional and indie, they would
take that book, query it, if it didn't
go anywhere, stick it in a um a pile and
query the next one and do that until
they had enough books to launch a career
indie publishing where you generally
need to do a big blitz at the beginning
and have a backlist that can sell off of
offering the first one free or heavily
discounted. that's still probably your
best method. Um, that said, indie
publishing has um is not as lucrative as
it once was. As a general body, it still
is. In fact, more people are buying
books across the board than they ever
have. More people are making a living at
writing uh fiction than they ever have
in the past. But there are a lot more
people publishing than there ever have
been before. And
um this means that the New York
publishers generally are in our
experience dropping authors
faster with even with decent
sales because the New York publishers
are focused so much more on best sellers
than they used to be. the sellers were
always important, but now, as I kept
keep saying with indie publishing taking
a bunch of the mid list, a lot of the
publishers can't make a living um or
make the money they they need on the mid
list. So, instead, they're dropping
authors and always hunting the new best
sellers. Meanwhile, the indie publishing
world has required more and more money
upfront than it used to. Uh, and more
and more money on ads and more and more
savvy on public the publicity end even
than it used to require. Um, so in some
ways it's the best time ever to try to
be a writer because like I said, more
people are making a living. Yet it seems
harder to break in than it ever has
before, which is a weird dichotomy. And
that might just be because the market is
so crowded. It favors those who have
momentum even more than it used to
because no longer do you have the
bookstore browsing as a kind of gateway.
Uh for the longest time, you could only
fit so many books on uh a bookstore
shelf. Therefore, you had a certain
number of sales you could count on just
by people browsing the new releases
shelf. Now the internet can hold any
number theoretically of released books
in a week and so uh this leads to just a
lot of crowding of the market. Uh I
don't want to be down on uh trying to
make it as a writer. Uh as I've said
before this is a this this class part of
the reason for it is to say yes you can
do this. That's what I needed to hear
from Dave when I took this class in uh
2000 was yes it's a real job. It's a job
you can do, but breaking in has never
felt as hard as it does now, uh, because
the market is so crowded. So, what would
I do? I would probably still, um, try a
hybrid approach. And I would, if you
were very serious about being
professional, learn what is selling in
indie and how right now people are
making uh, breaking in in indie, which
are things I can't answer. Um because uh
what what I'm not as familiar with is
what is working. I'm I'm familiar with
what worked five years ago, but learning
what works right now. It's like the
people in the trenches are doing that
right now. If uh India is not at all
interested interesting to you, then
hunting agents is your best uh goal. Um
and that is a miserable slog. Uh but
that is your best your best method of
breaking in. And to do that, I would
start looking at good conferences in
your region that regularly bring agents
out that offer things like pitch
sessions with that agent um and things
like that. Uh locally here in Utah
generally, uh writers for young readers
and story makers and futurecapes are
three of them that will consistently do
that. I have editors and agents out. uh
you'll have to look where you are and
find the ones, but those conferences
tend to be more expensive than other
cons. You can buy a ticket to ComicCon
for fairly cheap because they make all
of their money off of the vendor hall
and people spending there. The
conferences don't have that. They so
they make their money off of the ticket
sales. So, you pay a lot more to get
into one. So, that's what I would do
right now. Um is I would be I would be
studying a lot about the market. Don't
ever let that impact your writing. You
need to learn to be consistent, but I'm
assuming you are already consistent and
uh it's about how you want to break in.
What is a mistake you made as a writer
into get into publishing that you wish
someone would have warned you
about? The very first book I ever sent
to anyone was to an agent that I had not
done my research
on. And fortunately, they it didn't
didn't go anywhere, right? Um, but it
was an agent that um didn't live in New
York. And not all the best agents live
in New York, but most of them do because
as we talked about last week, generally
agents need to be keeping their finger
very closely on the pulse of publishing.
So, an agent living, and I'm not going
to say where they live. I don't want
someone to track them down, but in a
medium to smalls size town uh uh in the
region where I am could not sell my book
to anyone. And I won't go so far as to
call them a scam. Uh I will go so far as
to call them a well-meaning individual
who thought maybe they could help people
get published, but uh realistically was
just a waste of time. Uh so that was a
mistake I made. One of the other things
that I think slowed me down was not
learning to revise. Uh being kind of a
classic uh architect writer, I would
want finish a book and be like, "Oh, I
can just write the next book better than
this one." And would start the next
book. And the fact that um I
realized eventually the best writers I
knew were actually the best revisers.
They're the people that can take a good
book and make it excellent. Made me
really sit down and teach myself
revision, which is still my least
favorite part of the process. Uh, but it
wasn't until I learned revision, learn
to take a good book and make it great
that I got published. So, there's a
couple of those. Why don't we do a
couple here? Uh, if you guys have
questions. Yeah, go ahead. What would
you say is the best way to learn
revision then? Uh, best way to learn
revision. So this is partially um
unfortunately like everything else trial
and error. So you learn revision by
looking at feedback you get on a story
trying out some of that feedback and
seeing if it makes it it makes your
story better. And if it does say okay
why did that work? What what was good
about this feedback? And then trying it
a lot of times with different kinds of
feedback and seeing what makes your book
better and what doesn't. The trick about
this is generally you're not going to be
able to do this after you've written
only one novel because you won't have
the instincts yet for what makes a good
book or what works for you. And so in
part I don't know if I could have
learned it much earlier. You need to be
building instincts in yourself as a
writer that what what makes you write
good stories and then you need to have
enough experience so that when you do a
revision you know if it's better or not.
um soliciting more feedback can be
helpful on that. But again, beta readers
and this sort of feedback is not best
for everyone. It works very well for me,
so I emphasize it. Some authors hate it.
In this case, you find just a couple of
very good alpha readers. You trust their
instinct. You try revising and see if
you think the book is better, if that
makes sense. And so, it's just uh it's a
matter of of practicing and seeing what
makes a book better for me. What
different strategies? Try different
strategies of revision such as try the
10% cut. Is your book better if you go
line by line and try to cut 10% using a
spreadsheet out of every chapter? Is it
not? If you're a short story writer,
that probably won't make your book
better. A short story writer that jumped
to writing novels. For a lot of
novelists, uh that can force you to look
at your language and say, "Am I
repeating myself? Where's my passive
voice? Am I using too many um verbs that
don't mean anything?" and that sort of
stuff. Go ahead. Yeah. Um, kind of along
in that vein, um, I know that you've
shared like prior versions of your books
before, like King's Prime. Yep. Um, is
there any resources other than that? Do
you know like is it worth spending the
time to like read a first draft of some
of an author who's been share that and
then read the published work and like is
that is it worthwhile to read an
author's first draft and last draft? I'm
not 100% sure, but I thought it might
be. So, when we did um uh Shadows
Beneath uh a collection that we did, we
included every version of the story,
including a redline version that showed
what we changed. If this is valuable to
you, you might want to try picking up a
copy of that. Uh, I don't know if you
can find, you'd want to get the print
version cuz all four of our stories, um,
me, Dan, Howard, and Mary Robinette, we
did a version of first and last, so you
could so you could see that. And I know
mine has the track changes, um, like
strikethroughs and things like that. Um,
I hope that that's useful. I think it
might be hard to find consistently
um, ways to do that and, uh, ways to
study that. I think doing it yourself is
always going to be better than reading
someone else's but maybe that'll be
helpful. So there is a resource that we
have there. Go ahead. When you're
writing your stories like say the one of
the Stormlight novels, do you write it
in a linear fashion or do you write one
story arc and then another and then
splice them? Right. Do I write in a
linear fashion or do I write by story
arc and splice them? Uh Stormlight I
always write by story arc and splice
them. This is more work. I don't
recommend it except for the fact that I
have to do it on Stormlight because
there are so many characters that I feel
like um I would lose the threads of the
character arcs. So when I can write
straight through if there's only a
couple of threads, I will or I'll write
like one chunk and then jump. Um I have
found that the amount of revision I have
to do goes up if I write by uh story
arc. This is because there is a natural
sort of feeling of pacing you want to
have in a book. And once you're splicing
together a bunch of uh viewpoints, what
you will find is one viewpoint has a
nice pacing unto itself and then you mix
it with another one, it just messes up
the pacing um and in ways that take a
lot of work to fix. So yeah. Um you
mentioned that when you sign on with a
agent Yes. that they have the first
rights to the the books that you Yes.
When you sign up with an agent, you are
signing up as a person with an agent,
not for a specific book. So my question
is how did you handle that with your
secret projects? How did I handle that
with uh my secret projects? They were
not published. I didn't look for
contracts with New York. So the agenting
is uh and these were kind of a special
case. I don't know how all agents
respond, but I didn't go when I sold the
new the rights to New York. So, with the
secret projects, you'll see there are
editions in bookstores. I went through
my agent and when uh I self-publish
them, usually agents, and you can be
very upfront with agents, most of them
their contract won't include anything
you're indie publishing. You're just
completely uh blanket. And what they
want is if you're going to go handle
negotiations, if they're you're going to
use an agent, you're going to use them
is kind of what the contract is saying.
Did your secret projects affect your
relationship with your agent at all? Uh,
did my secret projects affect my
relationship? No. Uh, Joshua was well
aware. I do lots of indie publishing.
Um, and Joshua. Oh, look who it is.
Sorry, I shouldn't uh highlight you. Uh,
this is nobody important except the most
beautiful woman in the world.
Um, yay, Emily.
Um so no but I did inform him early. Um
Joshua was well aware of our uh strong
independent publishing uh thing and he
had been along for the whole journey. Uh
Joshua is also a bit of a strange duck.
Um and I say that with the most
affection possible. Everybody who knows
him is nodding. Um um Joshua is a bit of
strange duck and he basically lives to
be an agent. He has like no life other
than being an agent. I mean he does have
his board game night but I think he
canceled that even during co right like
he does he lives drinks breathes
everything. What can I do for my
clients? And it is always about what can
I do for them? He is very
serviceoriented. Um
and Joshua you know if there's a a place
that he there's not service he can a
service he can perform then he is
totally fine with that. and he's been
very clear with me. He doesn't want to
stand in the way of any of that. But he
also knows that I'll use him when I when
I need to. When we are having really
complicated contract negotiations with
Spotify because you know the whole
Audible thing, he handled those for us,
right? Uh and any contract he
negotiates, then he gets his cut of um
and there are authors for whom Joshua is
only their foreign agent. He doesn't
handle any of their US because they are
strongly independent published. Um, like
the Sullivanss I believe use him for
foreign agents and things like that. I
can't get quoted on that 100% but I
think Michael J. Sullivan that's what he
does. Um, and Joshua where he can be of
service he is of service and he he knows
he earns his money so he's not he he
doesn't feel insecure. Um, but you know
I think that the the relationship with
the publisher is more what someone would
want to worry about in that instance. Um
and we did approach them earlier um be
before everyone else and we explained to
what we're doing and they would of
course rather
us have done everything through them but
they knew and they know uh that they
can't handle everything that uh that my
aspirations will want to uh include. So
the I am a very strange case. In your
case, if you go with an agent, just make
it clear. I want to be indie publishing
also and I don't consider you know that
uh part of the agency contract and they
almost certainly will be just fine with
it. Mhm. Did your agent help you with
your Kickstarter campaign? Did my agent
help with the Kickstarter? No. We did
all of that ourselves. If he had helped,
um I would have expected him to take a
percentage.
Um, but at the same time, he doesn't
know Kickstarters. That's not a thing
that agents really do. That's an indie
publishing thing. And so I I I wouldn't
be surprised if more agents are learning
about it because of what we did. But
when we did it Kickstarter, there there
are definitely people who are doing it
before us and years and years and years
before us. But uh we did change the
market pretty dramatically when we did
it. So I wouldn't be surprised if more
are paying attention now. But back then,
an agent had would have had no idea what
to do with Kickstarter. Good question.
How is it that day you were so
successful with Kickstarter? How were we
so successful at Kickstarter? Okay, big
question. Let me uh break it down for
you. The first and most important thing
to be successful at Kickstarter is to
already have an audience.
Kickstarter generally is bad uh at least
in the arts for people who don't already
have a way of reaching an audience. Um
and so that's the most important with
some fields. You can have a Kickstarter
where you don't have an audience
already, but if you look at the top
Kickstarters in the creative fields,
they're all people who had audiences.
The things that go high that aren't are
some sort of big tech device. And in
those cases, the number two thing that
makes a Kickstarter successful is uh
managing to get press
coverage. Um press coverage is really
important for a crowdfunding campaign
like that. um we didn't need it as much
because we had the built-in audience.
But if you don't, then you have to be
appearing um in all the major like media
um and getting all this attention and
things like that in order to do very
well on Kickstarter or other
crowdfunding campaigns. So, there was
that. My video that I did at the start
was very good at going viral. Uh more so
even than I anticipated. um uh faking
out my fans and making them think that I
was that I was retiring uh turns out was
super mean, but it really made them want
to prank their friends and send the
video to them. And so having a really
big viral video was a super uh help. Um
but number three that makes a successful
crowdfunding is having the
infrastructure in place already to build
the thing and fulfill. Uh when
Kickstarters go wrong, it's because they
overestimate or I should say they
underestimate how much work it will take
and overestimate how much they can do.
And because of that, they don't factor
in the actual cost of the thing. They
don't factor in shipping costs
correctly. They don't factor in um all
of this stuff that can that syncs
Kickstarters. We were able to do it
because we had already for almost what
we had when did we laced our first one?
7 years. 7 years of already doing
fulfillment on our own books. Yeah. Cuz
Yeah. Um and so because we had already
had this whole infrastructure in place.
It meant that we knew what our
limitations were, how long it would take
us to get books, what it would take to
ship them and all of that. So for a
newer author, do I recommend uh
Kickstarter? I generally wouldn't
recommend Kickstarter until you have at
least a small audience. Once you have a
small audience, you can move to doing a
crowdfunding, but I would recommend
highly already having a business in
place where you sign people's books and
ship them to them so that you know what
it takes to take a load of books to a to
a mail room. Who's laughing? Yeah,
somebody is laughing. I'm looking over
here at some of my fulfillment team.
Like going to the post office with a
giant crate of books sometimes is uh you
need to make those contacts and things
like that and be doing that
consistently. So if you have a small
business uh as a writer and you're
selling ebooks, 10,000 copies a year,
it's where you know it's kind of your
threshold for really going pro as uh an
indie author. Um and you say I want to
do a Kickstarter for a print edition.
you're thinking that I would recommend
first getting some printed
uh for one of your books and saying, "I
have these. Let's start selling them on
my website signed to get you copies."
And get used to doing that before you do
the Kickstarter. And then you're um
you're kind of in this big position
where you need to fulfill on a deadline.
when you do Kickstarter, don't
overpromise on your rewards for the
Kickstarter. Um, that's another thing we
were very careful on. Um, building in
money for like when people do a
Kickstarter often it's like, "Hey, I
don't want just the thing. I want to get
extra cool stuff." Um, and so building
that in. So, there's a whole lot of
resources out there, but for an
author, get an audience first, even if
it's a small one, and then get
experience shipping to people before you
do it. You can, if you have a successful
Kickstarter, use some sort of
fulfillment group that you ship the
books to them and they fulfill for you.
They will take a large chunk of your
money. And I do not know how that works
because we haven't ever used one. So,
all right. Yeah. just from like a
writing as a business perspective, what
would you recommend especially for indie
or new authors in order to build that
audience? Building your audience as an
indie or new author. Um, so one thing
that I would recommend is kind of
deciding and you can't do all this
because some of this will be artistic
concerns. You will have artistic
artistic concerns override
um any business concerns. Okay. uh but
picking an idea that is your brand. What
is it that you are going to be doing? Uh
even if it's not
um not necessarily the only thing you're
doing like I do think it was
advantageous to me to be like hard magic
systems that we approach in interesting
ways from a lot of different viewpoints
are how Brandon's books are going to
work particularly early in his career.
And I kept a consistent tone uh across
the epic fantasies to build a brand and
say this is what you're getting. Uh and
I branched people out slowly, right? I
didn't do trust of the emerald sea right
early in my career. Uh and I do think
that was a help now that people are used
to reading uh a variety of things for
me. Releasing a book that has a wildly
different tone was super successful. Um
but you know if um I think early on
again artistic concerns set aside
building and saying this is what I do
consistently so that you can have people
start to associate your name with
something. Build a mailing list. Mailing
list should come before most other
social media presences in my opinion
because you have control over the
mailing list and the people who are
willing to sign up for it are the most
dedicated of the people. if they're
going to come and sign up for a mailing
list, then be good with your mailing
list. Um, consistently either send a
newsletter or, you know, at least just
inform people what you're doing and
things like that and make it good value
so that people want to open it, that
your newsletter is not spamming them,
that they're not getting something every
3 days like when you sign up for some of
these uh these new letters like you
know, you buy one thing off of
AliExpress. Congratulations. 10 emails a
day for the rest of your life, right?
Um, so don't be like that. Send a really
nice newsletter quarterly or something
like that or monthly or whatever it is
for your even if it's yearly
consistently good newsletter so that you
can then be able to say I have a new
book out. I would appreciate your
support. And here is the places where
you can find it on sale. So the
newsletter does value ads. So after
that, picking like um deciding if you're
going to be a platform writer or not. We
didn't talk about platform writing. Um,
platform writing is one of the ways that
you can make a name for yourself is by
having a platform that you speak about
on social media and upon on your blog.
Uh, during the early days of indie
publishing, a lot of people made their
platform I am forging the path in indie
publishing. Come to here to hear my uh
blog to hear about indie publishing.
That worked really well. You guys may
know Larry Korea. Um Larry uh came to
me. He was indie publishing uh way back
way back when and I uh had a couple
books out and he came to me and said, "I
think I want to try traditional
publishing here. Talked to me about it
and things like that." And we had a
really good conversation where he was be
in the days before indie publishing
doing really well indie publishing. And
I said, "How did you do this?" And he's
like, "Well, uh I like
guns." That's an understatement, right?
When I said to Larry, "Hey, I wanna um
I've never fired an automatic weapon
before and I'm writing a lot of books
where they exist. Can you, you know, uh
can I can you find a way for me?" He
brought like 30 automatic weapons,
okay, to a gun range with two of his
friends who were experts in historical
firearms and like a safety officer,
right? and set up a tent and he was so
excited and it was like just like fire
all the guns, right? And he knew every
one of those guns and he could tell me
all about them and things. This is
Larry. So Larry likes guns. What does
Larry not like? When people get guns
wrong in their fiction cuz he wants his
guns to be accurate. And he eventually
said, uh, I want to write books where
that are fun and exciting, but also they
get the guns right. And so he went to
the gunnut forums that he was part of
and was like, "Hey, would you guys read
a book if I did this?" And they're like,
"Yes, the guns, people use of guns drive
us up the wall, too. Write a book where
people, you know, shoot monsters and use
guns accurately." And so he did. And
then he went back to them and said,
"Hey, I wrote the book. It's this." And
a ton of them bought it. And suddenly he
um he became he started he blogged a
lot. Um and these days Larry's platform
is gunn nuts and yelling at people on
the internet. He's very good at that
too.
Um buy the book. Scar. Did you buy Did
you read Monster Hunter before it was a
Bane book? I went to a gun show to get
it physically.
Scar went to a gun show physically to
get it signed. Yeah. writes Larry's a
great writer too, but he also has this
platform, right? Uh, by the way, if if
you are of a certain inclination
politically that maybe doesn't overlap
with the people who love guns, you may
not like his blog. So, you may just want
to read his books and stay away from the
blog. I'll just uh tell you that. Um,
but he is a good example of what we call
a platform writer. Uh, another great
example of this is Corey Doctoro. Uh
Corey Doctoro uh was one of the in the
early days of blogging of professional
blogging. He was one of the first early
professional tech bloggers. He started
writing books kind of about open source
and he was one of the forces behind the
creative commons and things like this.
And his books very much sort of tie into
those sorts of things. Like he has a a
whole book about like gold farmers in
China for video games banding together
to make a union, right? the Gold Farmers
Union, stuff like that. Um, and so he
wrote books that align with what his
platform was as well. And so he would
blog and draw like-minded readers that
maybe are self- selecting into reading
his blog who might enjoy the stories
he's writing. And then he would release
the books. And that's what what I call a
platform writer. You are using something
you are passionate about that you write
about eloquently and interestingly as a
platform by which you sell your books.
And indeed most of you would call most
politicians, most YouTube uh authors and
things like that platform writers. But
you can be, you know, writer first and
platform second and still be a platform
writer. I only this is if you're going
to dig deep into social media, I
recommend you be a be wanting to do it
for platform writing reasons. Otherwise,
it will both suck your soul and uh your
time. Uh but if you have a niche that
you can get into that you can then
platform on and you enjoy that aspect of
it, you can then turn it into something
that will help you sell your books. Uh
if you are not then I recommend mailing
list, a website with um you know and a
minimal social media presence
um and not spending too much time on
those sorts of things. Do some
interactions. Um but one of the
questions you're going to have to ask
yourself is why would someone go to my
social media except to hear about my
books? Once you get big enough, it can
just be to hear about your books. But
people get so much so much information
and so much marketing that it's like,
you know, what what's the value you're
adding to their life? If you want people
to follow your social media and things
like that, if you're not sure what it
is, keep it to a minimum. Um, don't
invest too much effort in it. Maybe pick
one platform and do a good job with it.
Uh, you know, Tik Tok is the one right
now for books, particularly uh books of
a certain certain style. Um,
I didn't mean that to be a
joke, right? Certain things sell better
on Tik Tok. Um, meaning uh certain
styles of books like YA and new adult
sell really well on Tik Tok. Um, epic
fantasy sells worse on Tik Tok, but
romanty sells well, right? Book club
books, anything that someone can take to
their book club sell really well on Tik
Tok, right? Uh, so it's not like a
specific genre. It's just like you know
it when you feel it. what kind of book
like uh would would do really well on uh
as a thing and so if you're on Tik Tok
and you can make funny videos then you
can maybe platform uh with Tik Tok but
if not uh don't feel you have to do it
nothing will be better for your career
than writing the next good book but you
do have to do a minimum amount of this I
that's why I say mailing list keep a
website have sample chapters on the
website stuff like that thank you yeah
go ahead so do you see any value in
going to conferences out of state to
meet and talk to agents or can you find
that online? Do I find it any value in
going out of state to talk to agents at
conferences? This is going to depend on
the value of a dollar to you. meaning um
to a person who uh to whom a,000 bucks
once a year to go to a conference
outside of the state is not a hardship
then it's probably worth your time
because you will you will be able to go
to like the bigger the city generally
the better the conferences will be. We
are lucky in Utah that we have a pretty
vibrant writing community and so we have
I feel above average um conferences.
Generally areas where books sell well
will be the same. Pacific Northwest
tends to have a better than average um
writing conferences for that reason. Um
but otherwise you know New York,
Baltimore area, um Boston area pl you
know um places with large population
centers and uh things like that are
going to draw the agents cuz the flights
are easier, right? Um and East Coast is
going to draw more agents than West
Coast because the flights are easier.
They can hop on a train and they can,
you know, they can head up to head up to
Boston and do a conference up there. And
so watching for and learning, this is
one of the things I would say. Someone
said, "I want to break in." Learn the
names of the agents. Learn the names of
the agencies. Um, do what I said last
week and have your little black book um
that has a list of all the agencies that
are selling books right now by new
authors you can find in bookstores and
the agents who work there. And keep
track of of conferences that are
consistently getting these people. Put
them on your list to check every year to
see who the agents going. and then you
can spend the money. But there are some
people in this room for whom $1,000 is
just an enormous hardship. In that case,
um staying locally, uh if you happen if
you live here, if you live in one of
these other places I mentioned and going
to those, they will try to get different
agents every year. And your bang for
your buck is probably better at the
local ones, but you know, if you can
spend the money, uh this is an industry
that will take as much of your money as
you're willing to spend, so be careful,
right? Um but uh I do find value in it.
Conferences I elevate above cons right
now for professional development. Um I
am going to World Con this year. I'm
going to scope out how I feel it is for
new authors just by kind of watching uh
and seeing and uh hopefully you'll be
there too cuz you can tell me the new
agents that I don't know. um and be
watching and see who's there because
it's in Seattle which is a big enough
city that we might draw a decent number
of uh agents senators and then I'll know
better for next year uh in the pre-COVID
era what percentage are going to
WorldCon. Used to be Worldcon was one of
the better places to go and it might
still be uh but that's only if you know
how to network where the other ones you
don't have to actively network. you can
buy a slot in a pitch session uh with
that rather than find your way to a
party and see if you can find someone to
talk to who can actually help you with
your career. And that's hard and that's
really stressful. One of the most
stressful parts of my life was going to
these conventions and being like, I can
barely afford this. I need to walk out
of this having met editors and be able
to send my books to them. And that was
just like a giant boulder upon my back
at every one of the conventions.
Yeah. Uh what if anything can you get
away with changing between your first
and second books?
What can you get away with changing
first and second books? You can get away
with anything. That's how this industry
works. That's how the world works. Um
you can get away, but what are the
consequences, right? Um there are pros
and there are advantages and
disadvantages. there pros and cons to uh
to each each method. Um so what are the
pros to swapping? Training your audience
earlier and or having not all your eggs
in one basket are both very viable
reasons to have your second book be
different. I would recommend your third
book, not your second generally. Um if
you're going to if you really want to
write YA or middle grade and your other
is going to be adult, I would do two in
a row and then branch out. But if you
really want to branch out, this doesn't
put all your eggs in one basket. Uh
there was a point in my life where I
thought I was going to turn into a
middle-grade author because Misbornne
was not selling. And the Alcatraz versus
Evil Librarians contract had been uh had
been for 40 grand per book, which is
basically that's getting to where I
could live on that money, right? And so
I'm like, well, I guess I'm a
middle-grade author now. Uh but then,
you know, I lost my editor at
Scholastic. she moved to another thing
and the new editor and I didn't click uh
very well and the uh though the first
Alcatraz book just sold tons the second
Alraz book barely sold
anything which is why I eventually
bought the series back and gave it uh to
tour. Um so yeah um what
uh what are they the the what are the
cons? Well, the cons are what I
mentioned a little earlier, which is if
you're starting to build a fan base,
giving them something to latch on to to
remember who you are can be really
valuable. Uh, having them say, "Wow, I
like this book and I like this book and
I like this book." Means that they'll
start to look for your books and things
like that. they will accept if you're
like if they see a middle grade, a lot
of them just won't buy it and then and
they'll look for your next adult one. As
long as you got one coming, you can be
fine. It's not super dangerous, but
those are your pros and your cons,
right? Uh, another one I haven't talked
about uh that is val uh v valuable to
think about is in the days before you
publish, this might be even more
valuable to you. Let's say you're set on
traditional
publishing. Do you want to write all
your books in one series or not?
Right? Uh I get this question now and
then it's worth thinking about and let
me give you two case studies about this.
I early on thought well if I write a
sequel to Alantress I can't send it to
the editors who rejected
Alantress but if I write a different
book and they like Alantress or whatever
even though they reject it I can send
them this other book that's not a
sequel. So my philosophy was write a
whole bunch of first books that have SQL
potential. That just gave me more books
to be submitting out to the world. Um
Naomi Novik did not do that. Naomi uh
who is uh breaking in around the same
time as me wrote uh Terrare. If you
haven't read them, uh they're very good
books. They are uh Patrick O'Brien, you
know, naval master commander except with
a dragon air force. It's about the
dragon air force. Uh what's that? So
much better. Yeah, they are very very
good. Um, yeah, everything's better with
dragons. Um, she's a very good writer.
She's written a she can write very
widely in a lot of different things, but
when she was uh trying to break in, she
wrote temporary. And again, I'm going
off of like third-hand accounts. I can't
remember if I've even asked Naomi about
this, but she, as I understand, then
just wrote the sequel and just wrote the
third one and then sent them in and a
publisher, she had all her eggs in one
basket. The publisher wanted the first
one. She said, "I have two more." And
the publisher was like, "Wow, these are
all great. We have three books. We can
launch you big." And they did the indie
publishing thing back before indie
publishing was was a thing. They
launched like her first book like one
month and their second book was like two
months later or even the next month and
her third book was like two months after
that. She they launched them all in
paperback and just flooded every market
with them. They didn't do the
traditional here's a big prestige hard
coverver. It's like paperback,
paperback, paperback. And because they
had all three, they were able to
leverage a lot of um kind of internal
going to all their marketing teams and
things like that. And they got cover
blurbs from um as I remember, you have
to uh look this up and double check me,
Stephen King, Anne McAffrey, and Terry
Brooks, which for that era, just like if
your blurbs are Stephen King and
Macaffrey and Terry Brooks say read this
book, right? So she just exploded onto
the scene um with this just huge
marketing blitz, which is the way indie
authors now do it. release a bunch of
books really fast kind of as lost
leaders to build a career out of. Um,
and so you can see that that both have
pros and cons. If someone had rejected
the first temper, they're not going to
look at the second temporary. But when
she did sell, she had this backlog of
great books that then she was able to
leverage into bursting just huge on the
scene. This is why she stomped me for
the Hug or the not a Hugo. Uh, they
don't even call it the Campbell anymore.
whatever they call the rookie of the
year award uh nowadays. Um what it is
what's it new author the new author
award. Okay that's that's really boring.
They should just make it a Hugo for best
new author. This is what everyone's
always said. Uh but that's why she
stomped me. And the other person who
stomped me was Scholsey my
nemesis. And Scholsey was a platform
writer. He was uh this is going to date
us. AOL's prof official professional
blogger. He wrote professionally for AOL
as their blogger and on his own blog he
just started serializing his novel he'd
written. Uh and an editor's like uh stop
serializing this. I'm going to buy it.
Uh I might be shortcutting some things.
I think he wasn't planning to put the
whole novel up. But uh and that's how he
sold by having a built-in audience
already. So of course when he when we
were all up for the awards, he also
stomped me. Um and so that he became my
nemesis. All right, other questions. Go
ahead. Um, so I get really confused and
I've tried to straighten this out
looking online, but I I get really
confused what delineates if it's going
to be YA, middle grade, right? Okay, let
me talk you through. Uh, the middle
grade YA one is uh is much easier to
delineate. Okay, middle grade are books
that kids are reading that are given to
them generally by adults uh that they
know. Okay. the age at which so the line
between YA and middle grade is that line
where the kid doesn't want to get a book
from a teacher anymore and wants to go
read the book that they're not given.
Okay. Um and so middle grade is
generally and it is a bit fuzzy but you
can see um it generally covers maybe
fifth grade definitely sixth and seventh
grade maybe eighth grade. Uh right it
can go as low as fourth grade. So Harry
Potter 1 is middlerade, but by Harry
Potter 4, it's actually YA. Um, age of
the protagonist minus two or three or
sometimes one is about your uh your age
group. Kids like to read about kids
older than them as a rule of thumb. All
of this gets broken. I think LRA from
Dark Materials is like eight, right? Uh
Ender is like what, eight or something?
Say starts at six. When's he go to
battle school, though? Okay. Yeah,
that's like eight or nine. And that's
that's considered YA. Okay. Um and so
really it's books targeted at a certain
um age group. And so once kids stop
reading what are handed them by adults
and want to find them on their own or
get them from friends, that's the big uh
YA tradition. Another couple transition.
Another couple of things is um
middle-rade puppy love, yes. Dating, no.
Generally, this is the age group where
kids are like starting to be interested,
but they aren't they don't want stories
about that. Is this a kissing book?
That's middle grade, right? Right. Where
by the end they're probably okay with a
kiss, right? Um and um ya is fullon
romance. Uh ya is generally coming of
age. I have to learn how to be an adult.
Middle grade is gen generally whimsical
adventure where the parents are either
idiots or locked away
somewhere,
right? Um um and so that's kind of your
differentiation. One other thing is YA
is not edited for content despite what
people may think. Some YA lines are and
some um authors, you know, but a YA book
doesn't mean clean. A middle-grade book
does. Uh, ya, middle grade is generally
edited for content. In fact, I don't
know of any that aren't. Uh, YA lines
generally aren't. That doesn't mean you,
you know, you can write whatever you
want and plenty of clean YA cells, but
you shouldn't assume that YA means uh,
clean. Um, and then the transition from
YA to new adult is real fuzzy and then
into adult. These just kind of turn into
marketing um things. Generally, YA needs
to get to the point faster. It does
generally use fewer
viewpoints and it generally digs deep
into one maybe two characters
experiences very deeply as they are
transitioning from child to adult. Um
and that's kind of the hallmark of what
makes YA. But I mean, Andrew's Game is
YA. His Dark Materials is YA. Uh, who
knows, right? Uh, Wheel of Time would
fit that, but it's published as adult,
right? Um, like it's at that point, it
kind kind of becomes marketing sort of
stuff and you talk the marketing.
Shannon Hail famously submitted Goose
Girl to tour as an epic
fantasy. You guys don't read Shannon
Hail enough otherwise you'd be laughing
at that. Go read Shannon. Her books are
great. Uh, this is a fairy tale
retelling. Uh, and they're all like, um,
make your protagonist a teenager and
submit it to Bloomsberry. And she did
and she got published, right? Um, so
yeah. What if you want to write like a
more non-traditional way? There's like
because I know an example is like
Cormack McCarthy. He wrote for years not
making money, but now his books are more
like popular than ever after he's dead.
Like is that style now now profitable?
Is that style now profitable? Cormarmac
McCarthy. So, I mean, Cormarmac McCarthy
is one of the greats, right? Um, and um,
Cormarmac McCarthy is just like such a
bizarre story, right? No quotes, right?
Uh, just breaking all the rules and
things like this, but it works. Um, is
that style more marketable now than it
used to be? Um, I don't know. I can't
speak to literary fiction, what's
marketable or not. I know that Norah uh
NK Jameson has done a very good job
selling very well in science fiction
fantasy as um literary. So if there's a
line that which is a fake line that
doesn't exist, but it kind of separates
literary science fiction fantasy from
science fiction fantasy that has some
literary pros, she's definitely on the
literary side. Um whereas someone like
Pat Rothus is on the commercial side
with literary pros and she is she sells
very well. She writes very good books.
Um I would say that in sci-fi fantasy uh
NK JSON is selling as well as she does
has helped make a market for literary
fantasy. Uh but you could make the
argument that the Ursula Leguin was
doing that for years and years and years
and Octavia Butler and some of these and
Gene Wolf. Um, and that there's always
been a market. It's just why does some
things take off and some things don't is
really hard to figure out. Uh, why did
it take people long so long to figure
out Cormack McCarthy's books were
amazing? I don't know. I haven't studied
that market. But I can tell you there's
a whole lot like Jane Austin
was started off writing for her family
and only right before she died did she
start to get popular. Right. Uh, and
that that unfortunately happens a ton to
artists. So, die faster. What's that?
Oh, you should just die faster. Okay,
let's let's not let's not take that as
uh this. We'll go here and then over
here. What's your opinion on trying to
publish at Shadow Mountain or small?
Let's talk about small presses. So there
are um there's actually uh several ranks
of presses and they I would call Shadow
Mountain for those who watching on the
videos who don't know. This is a
regional press um headquartered in Salt
Lake, but they they cover more of a
range than a small press generally does
and they generally have hardcover um or
no paperback contracts with New York
publishers. So basically they'll handle
the the hard coverver distribution and
then they'll use the channels of the big
publisher. So there are a bunch of kind
of midsize presses that do this for the
longest time. Dah Dah was one of the big
forces in sci-fi fantasy. They published
Pat Rothus. They published Tad Williams
um and things like this. Um and they
were at indie that was not one of the
big five or big six but had a
distribution partnership of some manner.
I don't know all the details with Random
House, Penguin Random House. And so they
could release their books out wide as if
they were one of the big five, but they
were not. And so there are some like
this that are not one of the big five
that can do things like that. Uh I do
locally, particularly if you're writing
middle-grade or YA, recommend Shadow
Mountain. Um, I've known enough people
that have uh that have been there that
have been pleased with their experience
and I've seen enough people go fully pro
from Shadow Mountain to say that Shadow
Mountain is a good place to publish.
Watch out for your contracts. When you
get a contract, make sure you have an
agent. They aren't always the most
upto-date on what current contract
should look like. I'll say that. Um,
their advances generally tend to be
smaller. Um, and they do generally um
use a lot more uh school visits and sort
of grassroots marketing. Um, but I do
recommend them. Um, I don't know of a
lot of other regional presses that work.
DAW DAW's had financial troubles lately,
but they're still a very good publisher.
Uh, Bane that I mentioned before
functions like this. Um, generally if
it's smaller than those, I don't
recommend them except for specialty
books. Um, this is because for the most
part, and your mileage may vary, there
are some very good small presses out
there. And sometimes you can be the name
that helps launch a small press to a mid
mid press. Uh, this happened with Joe
Abberrombi and uh, Py. um the small
press that became a mid-level press that
started to be a force in the market
because Joe Abberi uh that they got the
US rights started selling so well um and
you can be that but in general in the
internet era publishing with a small
press is essentially the same as indie
publishing minus you getting indie
publishing
royalties. So I don't recommend it
because you will need to do all the same
work that you need to do. Uh the reasons
to publish with a small press. Number
one, you have something that just does
not sell well otherwise, but the
prestige of the right prestigious small
press can do it. Uh some of them do very
well, special editions. Some of them do
short story collections or an example of
something just doesn't generally sell
well, but having a small press behind it
can lend it prestige and actually help
sales on a short story collection. Um
sometimes nollas work very well with
small presses. Um, and just watch for
ones that are reputable. I've worked
with Tachion and I can say they were
excellent. Um, this is a small press um,
out of uh, San Francisco. Um, I think
it's San Francisco. Might be LA. I can't
can never remember. Um, but they do they
do a very good job. Um, but I wouldn't
publish my first epic fantasy novel with
Taken as much as I like them because in
general, you're just going to have to do
all the same things that you would do
indie publishing. you're gonna have to
do all that work yourself because yeah,
if what you want is to have a nicel
looking book that someone else does all
the work for that you're not trying to
make a career out of this, a small press
that loves your uh book and wants to
just give it the best cover and the best
editing it can and you all know that in
the best case it's going to sell a
thousand copies, that's totally fine,
right? Uh but it just depends on your
mileage may vary. Okay.
Okay. Um, this is a more personal
question for you. Um, today you signed
my copy of Misborn. Yes. And in it you
wrote, "I am hope." Yep. And you're of
course referencing your character,
Kelsier. I put that one in quotes. It's
him, not me. Yeah.
So he says, "You can't kill me. I
represent the thing that you've never
been able to kill. No matter how hard
you try, I am hope." Mhm. With this in
mind, what would you say is your biggest
objective as a writer? My biggest
objective as a writer is to tell good
stories. Um, tell good stories and make
good So, I actually got asked something
similar on this on a podcast just
recently.
Um, I know I look out at the sea of
faces and I know all of you want to be
where I am, right? Um, and statistically
most of you can't be. I have been given
the shot to be in this uh in this
position and um see yeah I was I'll I
I'll I'll talk a little bit after
another question kind of wrapping up but
I know you all want to to be here and so
I need to make good on having gotten
this opportunity
um and do a good job with it uh out of
respect for all of you who would happily
take the spot if I didn't do a good job
with it if that makes sense. So, I just
want to do the best job I can with my
stories. Yeah. Okay. Let's go over here.
How reasonable is it to include things
like maps or diagrams or sketches with
your submission to a publisher? Um,
maps, diagrams, sketches for a
submission to a publisher. Uh, this is
all going to depend on your caliber of
artistic
talent. Um, and we laugh about that, but
if you are not of a professional
caliber, I would not send any of that
with a submission. If you are a
professional caliber and you know you
even particularly if you have
professional credits as an illustrator
then it's value ad um and they will want
to see it um otherwise you don't want to
do that generally. Um I
recommend if you sell with a New York
publisher that you commission any art
for the interior of your book yourself.
let them handle the
cover. I recommend you work with that
artist and get copyright to it or at
least licensing rights to it for all
foreign publications and future uh
editions of the book. So, and keep that
contract handy so that you know like I
love to protect artist rights. I don't
like that a lot of places uh take
artists uh you know copyright away but
in this case you should get a work for
hire and have the copyright because you
don't want to have to write if you sell
in 30 countries just being able to
provide that map is is going to
streamline the process so much. So, I
recommend paying well, getting a nice
map. Uh, and same thing with some
interior, whatever interior art you
want, and then having that copyright
yourself so that you can, um, so that
you can put it in all the books in all
the different countries and things. All
right? You can trust the publisher to do
it. Your mileage may vary. I'm glad that
I don't. On a similar note, if you're a
writer, but you're also our illustrator.
Yeah. for for a project and uh like like
I pre- illustration so that's going to
be professional as well. Um how easy
would it be to get traditionally
published that way or would it be easier
to do indie publishing when you're
writer and illustrator for a project
that's not a children's book? If you're
a writer and
illustrator, is it better to indie
publish or New York publish if you want
to do both? Um and I'm glad you left out
the exclusion of children's books. Do be
aware that except in rare cases they
children's book publishers meaning um
children's books in the industry by the
way is 18 and under. So just be aware
that's how the vernacular goes
children's publishing. So picture books
you want in picture books they do not
want art with the text. They want one or
the other unless you've really proven
yourself. They're more okay with it
nowadays than they used to be but they
used to just really hate it. Now they
only mildly hate it. Um, if you're
publishing in adult science fiction
fantasy and your sketches are of a
professional caliber, no one's going to
complain. They might not let you do the
cover because a cover um, I don't think
I've talked about this yet. The cover is
not an illustration of your book. Write
that down and underline it. The cover is
a movie poster for your book. Just like
Luke Skywalker never stands holding a
lightsaber like this um in Star Wars.
Your book cover is not an
illustration. It is a marketing piece
and its job is to capture the right
mood. It's your first tone promise for
an audience. You can if you want argue
that your character's left-handed, not
right-handed. They got it wrong on the
cover. But when you do finicky things
like
that, you're maybe misunderstanding.
Okay. Interior art they're much more
okay with. I would still do my
submission without it unless it's
integral, right? Unless it's like um
partially graphic novel in some way that
you have to have it. Like Way of Kings,
even with as much art as I have, I
wouldn't have submitted with the art. Uh
but if it was a step beyond Way of
Kings, I probably would have included
it. Uh like Illuminae, it's not art, but
Illumina wouldn't work without all the
redactions and all of this sort of
stuff. Um, that's a famous one that um I
I think I talked about last week. Um, so
in your case, um, if they love the book,
send them the illustrations. Say, I
intend to illustrate my this myself
before you send the sign the contract.
Make sure they're cool with it. It's
basically what I'd say. And any
publishing can do whatever you want. So
uh in any publishing you can do it but
um authors historically have not been as
good at understanding their limitations
in visual mediums as uh they think they
are. Meaning a lot of authors think
they're better illustrators than they
are. So I'll just leave that with you.
Uh that said Christopher illustrated all
of his books I believe and did the
original covers. Uh this Christopher
Yeah, it's extra hot today for whatever
reason. Um, so it can be done. Um, and I
would say if it's interior art and
you're you're good at it, no one's going
to complain. And if they do complain,
make it an in world artifact. Just be
like, this the character is not as good
as the professional artist you want to
hire, but this is their art. Uh, they
might be more okay with that, right? Go
ahead. What suggestions do you have for
consuming art in order to especially
books to learn better how characters and
plot work? What advice? I mean do I have
when you're consuming books read widely
read outside your genre but don't read
only outside your drama genre watch what
people are doing and start to think
critically about books critically not
meaning this is terrible say why did the
author do this make the assumption that
the author is making the choices
deliberately they aren't always but
where criticism comes it's usually
better to go into the assumption of the
author did this why did they do this why
might they have done what would I have
done differently or what can I learn
from what they did? Um, and just start
consuming media that way. Uh, you're
probably doing it already. I don't know
that I can give you more advice than
that. Uh, because the more you do and
the more you write, uh, you will hit
this bump where reading stops being fun
for you like it used to be because now
it's work. You will generally, if some
are in that, uh, you you generally will
get over that and then it'll come back.
Most authors I know the difference is uh
if we compare my wife to me as readers,
she has to finish anything she starts no
matter what the quality is. Uh that's
that's very common among readers. Among
writers, we give up on books way
earlier. We read a little bit, be like,
I'm not learning anything from this. I'm
done. Uh and we put it aside. Uh and
that that's often one of the changes
that happens to you. So um so yeah. All
right, other questions. since we got
just a couple minutes left. I I've had a
dream for a while to write a book sort
of like Percy Jackson in the sense that
anyone who reads it just learns about a
topic extensively. Okay. Do you have any
advice for a project like that? You want
to write a book like Percy Jackson where
someone who reads it learns about a
topic extensively. Story comes first,
topic comes second. If you're not a good
storyteller first, doesn't matter what
the topic is. That would be my
recommendation to you. Learn to write a
compelling story, but then pick
something you're passionate about. Um,
make sure you're using all the tools
we're talking about where you're not
overwhelming with too much. Make sure
the story comes first. You'll it'll
probably be a value ad if you do it that
direction. So, yeah. Uh, how do you
prevent getting scammed by publisher
companies? How do you prevent being
scammed by publisher companies? Don't
give them any money. Don't use publisher
companies. Just don't is my my blanket
recommendation. Um, find reputable
editors who have worked on projects with
reput reputable indie
authors that charge a um a standard fee.
Generally, it's by word or by page. I
can't remember. Oh, it's by word. Um, by
word. Um, have give them a sample, pay
them to do the sample or see if they do
one for free. Usually, just pay them to
do a sample. They get back and then hire
that. Okay. pay pay money for that and
if you and then like a proofread copy
edit uh if you do that separately. Um
again people who have worked who have
good um you know good
pedigree buy uh
artwork from a reputable artist. Um
oftent times you can get it cheaper by
buying something that's not an exclusive
license, right? uh finding people who
are working, you know, like sometimes uh
back in the day it was Deviant Art, now
it's uh what's that other place? Art
Station. Art Station. Uh Art Station is
the good one. Deviant Art's terrible
now. Um it used to be good. Um but now
it's terrible. Uh sometimes you will be
able to find people on Art Station.
They're like, "This is concept art I did
for myself. You can go be like, "Hey,
what's non-exclusive license to use this
for cover art cost?"
Um, and sometimes like we would do this
and they come back and be like, "It's 50
bucks." And you're like, "For this
professional caliber piece?" They're
like, "Yeah." Um, and you'd be like,
"What's exclusive?" They're like, "Uh,
exclusive only for book covers. You can
sell it to anything else." They're like,
"Oh, you know, 250." And then you can
get this like fantastic book covers. I
haven't done that in a while. Um, but
sometimes you can do things like that.
um you know or if you're lucky or not
lucky if you if you are writing in a
field that doesn't require an
illustrated cover they can be
photography based you can sometimes find
people who are making professional
caliber covers for pretty cheap using
stock imagery that they buy and
manipulate but pay for your cover cover
title lettering and things your cover
design separate from your artwork. So
cover design artwork uh substantive
editor copy editor those are the things
you pay for. Did I miss anything? No.
Don't pay for anything else. Okay. Don't
pay for a company that says they can do
this all for you. Do it yourself. If
you're in your publishing, you are now a
small business owner. Do it yourself.
They will um the your chances of getting
scammed plummet if you do what I just
said. And particularly if you ask other
indie authors for who they're using for
their editors so that you can get those
uh recommendations. Okay. Uh, don't pay
agents, don't pay publishers, pay
editors and artists. You'll probably be
fine right here. Yeah, we got a little
time. What about using AI art for What
about using AI art?
Um, so,
um, I'll try to be as even-handed as I
can. Right now, you cannot own a
copyright for an AI AI created image.
Um, and that's being contested in the
courts. Um, AI art is generally been
trained on the work of artists who
object to that training and for that
reason is highly unethical if not
illegal yet. Um and so uh what do I say?
I say there are enormous ethical
concerns to using AI art. Um and you
can't have a copyright for it um anyway.
Um
and right now a art looks very much like
a art and it'll make you look
unprofessional. So all things are
stacked in it. That last one will
change, but I don't know if the first
two will. So I recommend against that.
Uh I think you are much better off
buying a package to a stock image um
website, buying licenses to use the
stock image images and building a book
cover that
way than using the AR. But um that is
it's hard for me to be evenhanded
because I know so many of the artists
who are so upset about the art being
trained the AI being trained on their
art without their permission. So uh
yeah, go ahead. Uh if you were to go
back to the early days of writing, what
good practices would you establish for
the organization of your thoughts and
ideas? Uh organization of my thoughts
and ideas. I think this is going to be
too individual to the individual. Um I
don't know what I would do like back
then I just used a word file. Um I found
a wiki more helpful for me after I moved
to that. But uh I would say more
important than organizing your thoughts
is like what makes you productive,
right? And so try the different
programs, try the different and try a
word document, try the post-it note
method, you know the q or the index
cards method. Not usually post-it notes.
people have index cards that they they
they use. Try a bunch of these things.
See what makes you productive. See what
doesn't distract you from the writing
and do that. All right. All right. We're
going to stop the Q&A there. Uh and I'm
just going to talk at you for five
minutes.
Okay.
Um how did we begin? We began with me
telling you that as we enter this class,
we are going to prepare pretend that you
are a professional for the course of
this class. you're allowed to let that
go now and go back to like whatever your
um your actual goals are. You have
hopefully this information. These
lectures are online. You can rewatch
them. I say this
because I want to both inspire you and
be a
realist. Almost certainly several people
in this room will go pro. statistically
watching what's happened. That said,
going pro doesn't necessarily even mean
making a living. A lot of people sell a
bunch of books and have a professional
credit but still have a day job. Um, and
I got a comment on one of these YouTube
videos recently that someone's like,
"So, wait a minute. You're telling me I
think they just watched the first
one. I need to work for 10 years to
learn how to be a writer. work for years
and years, maybe another decade to sell
a book and then I'll finally have that
book come out and I might not even make
a living. I'll make like 5 to 10 grand
and then the next ones and that one
might flop and I won't even have a
career after doing that. What kind of
maniac would do this? Right. And yes,
right. I cannot be here and sell you a
dream if that dream is being a
professional author. There are there are
thousands of people outside that door
that will try to sell you this dream.
There are the people that want you to
give them money in order to learn the
secrets of publishing. There aren't any.
Okay? The secrets of publishing are work
hard, be diligent over a long period of
time, then get lucky. Okay? And even now
I cannot tell you what percentage of me
getting published was diligent effort
mixed with skill and what part was the
luck. It could be 9010 on
either pretend I didn't
go. It could be 9010 on either
direction. Right? I think I worked hard.
I think I have natural talent.
I can't tell you how what percent that
was behind my success. And so when you
leave
today, you're going to have to at some
point either you've done it or you're
going to need to do it in the future.
You're going to have to make that
decision that I did back when I was just
finishing book 12. Do you guys remember
the
story where I realized, "Oh man, 12
books and not published. What am I
doing? Right? Should I have learned my
lesson by now? And I did. I learned the
lesson of I am writing because it is
good for me. I'm writing because this is
what I've built my self-identity around,
a talent I have and an interest I have.
I think it is legitimately good for me
to do and I am passionate about it. And
I made that decision that I was going to
keep writing for the rest of my life
even if I never sold a book.
And if you are writing to sell a book,
that's not enough. Certainly you can
want. I desperately wanted to and you
know most of you in this room I would
guess desperately want to or at least
very much so want to. That's not enough.
You have to in this business be writing.
If someone came to you today and said
you are never going to
publish, but your friends and family
will enjoy the books that you
write. Are you still willing to? You
have to be somebody who's willing to say
yes to
that
because you know statistically a couple
of you will make it. That's two out of
what? 200.
And those two are going to fight likely
for 10 to years to even see if they can
make it as a pro. Uh, talk to Rachel
Lynn sometime about what it's like to
sit there in those trenches and fight
even after you feel like you've made it.
And it's excruciating. I went through
that with Misbornne and I came out the
other end uh as again one of the lucky
ones. So that's the sad part, right? I
am also here to inspire. This can be
done. I was in one of those chairs in
2000. I didn't know what I was doing.
Dave gave me the information and I took
it and I sold. I would not have done so
if he hadn't been a told me it worked.
It can be done. And it is not a one ina-
million shot. It's more like one in a
hundred of of very serious
professionals. You can do it. And if you
can't control the market, which none of
us can, what you can control is the
satisfaction you get from writing,
getting better with every story,
building good habits, and being proud of
the things that you
create. I would get bet there are
millions of people in the world who want
to write a book, and I would bet less
than 1% of them do. If you finish a
novel, you are among the elite and you
are my colleague. So, make that your
goal and we'll see where it goes from
there. Thank you for taking the class.
Good luck in your writing journey.
[Applause]